A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Program Files (Non-Grant), RG 5 FA1799
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Program-Related Files, 1975-2019; 6; 32.9 Cubic Feet 94 containers
  - Community Partners Program, 1999-2011; 5; 5.74 Cubic Feet 16 containers
    - Community Partners Program - General, 1999-2011; 5.3
      - Akron, OH, 2008 January 17-February 29 (Box 3, Folder 9)
        Information on the Akron Biomedical Corridor, a significant KF project, consists of a project overview and statement of principles and intent (1/17/2008); a presentation document on the Akron Academic Health Center (as the project is now known) dated 1/25/2008, along with a meeting list and participant information and briefing report; and an update document prepared by Booz Allen Hamilton.
      - Black Males Initiative Working Session, 2011 April 18 (Box 3, Folder 10)
        Knight File Number - 5594
        Agenda; executive summary: research findings and design principles; participant biographies and participating organizations. The pilot communities were Detroit and Philadelphia. Also included are interviews of 20 black men from Detroit and Philadelphia briefly describing their projects (2 DVDs).
      - Crossroads Charlotte, 2011 September 6 (Box 3, Folder 11)
        Knight File Number - 4973
        Presentation: Learning from Crossroads Charlotte: A mini-teaching case for foundation staff prepared by Leila Fiester for the Knight Foundation. Evaluation of a series of grants to this organization, which totalled $ 3.6 million over seven years. Includes background of the grant, and lessons learned.
  - Education, 1986-2006; 6; 2.09 Cubic Feet 5 letter document boxes and 1 half-letter box
    - Advisory Committee Files, 1988-2000; 6.1
      These folders contain correspondence relating to the acceptance of Dr. John Porter to the Education Advisory Committee, and lists of all members of the committee and their terms as of March 1994 and 1995.
      - Membership Lists, 1988-2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 769
        Membership lists for the Education Advisory Committee, 1994-2000.
      - Correspondence with Education Advisory Committee members, 1992 February 24-2000 September 29 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 768
        Correspondence from Creed Black and, later, Hodding Carter about the recruitment and appointment of Education Advisory Committee members. Included are two memos from Rick Love re: Review of Education Goals, Objectives and Strategies, 1995-1999 and Revised Vision Statement. The last letter informs the members that, in light of the Board of Trustees' actions, the EAC has been disbanded.
      - Education Advisory Committee Meeting Minutes, 1998 September 23-2000 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 4080
        Minutes and attendees.
    - Endowments, 1994-2006; 6.2
      Files contain information on the establishment of an endowment for the University of North Carolina (Chapel Hill) for the William C. Friday Distinguished Professorship in Child Development and Family Studies.
      - University of North Carolina (Chapel Hill) #93-307, 1994 February 24-June 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 255
        Background re. endowment of William C. Friday Distinguished Professorship in Child Development and Family Studies at the University of North Carolina (Chapel Hill, #93-307). File contains news releases, tribute, announcement of fundraising campaign. Mr. Friday was Chairman of Knight Commission on Intercollegiate Athletics, 1989-1994.
      - Knight Non-Journalism Chair Inventory: Summary Report by Virginia Fielder, 2006 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 4319
        The report was undertaken to help the Foundation better understand the current status of these fourteen chairs, including the financial performance of each endowment, other contributors to the endowment, the academic unit in which each chair is located, the current holder of each chair and a brief summary of each chair holder's professional activities.
    - Initiatives - School Readiness, 2000-2001; 6.3
      - School Readiness in Miami: A Brief Overview and Highlights, 2000 December (Box 4, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 4311
        Report was prepared by Child Trends. The purpose of the report was to learn about school readiness efforts and practices in Miami. Child Trends conducted telephone interviews with expert informants over a two-month period.
      - School Readiness in St. Paul: A Brief Overview and Highlights, 2001 March (Box 4, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 4312
        Report was prepared by Child Trends. The purpose of the report was to learn about school readiness efforts and practices in St. Paul, MN. Child Trends conducted telephone interviews with expert informants and did a site visit to observe the programs targeted to young children and families.
    - Initiatives - Excellence in Education, 1988-1999; 6.4
      The Excellence in Education initiative was established to support the Knight Foundation's belief that colleges and universities have the capacity and responsibility to be effective collaborators in efforts to strengthen public schools.
      Files include those from CAPHE (Consortium for the Advancement of Private Higher Education), program overviews (1994), planning and proposals, summaries of grants (1997), and the School College Collaboration Conferences, 1997-1999.
      - CAPHE (Consortium for the Advancement of Private Higher Education), 1988-1996 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
        Knight File Number - 1631
        Folders contain correspondence with the staff of CAPHE (Consortium for the Advancement of Private Higher Education) about the creation of a Knight Foundation Education program. This was the early development of the Excellence in Undergraduate Education program. 2 folders.
      - Initiative Planning, 1991 July 15-October 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Knight File Number - 1632
        Correspondence about the planning of the Excellence in Education initiative, 1991.
      - Proposal Review Process, 1992 January 15-November 4 (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Knight File Number - 1634
        Documents recording the proposal review process for the Excellence in Education Initiative, 1992.
      - AAHE School College Collaboration Conference, 1993 December 5-8 (Box 1, Folder 17)
        Knight File Number - 1626
        Meeting materials for the American Association for Higher Education's (AAHE) School College Collaboration Conference held in Pittsburgh, PA, December 5-8, 1993.
      - Proposal Review Process, 1993 January 20-November 4 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        Knight File Number - 1633
        Documents from the proposal review process for the Excellence in Education initiative, 1993.
      - Excellence in Education: Update on the Program, 1993 November 4 (Box 1, Folder 19)
        Knight File Number - 734
        Memo from A. Richardson Love to the Distribution Committee on the changes in the Excellence in Undergraduate Education Program. It includes descriptions of the changes in the competition, analysis of issues addressed in proposals, a summary of institutional participation since 1992 by geography and type of institution, and preliminary planning for 1994.
      - AAHE School College Collaboration Conference, 1994 November 17-20 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 1625
        Meeting materials for the American Association for Higher Education's (AAHE) School College Collaboration Conference held in Washington, D.C., November 17-20, 1994.
      - Program Overview, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 1559
        Overview of the Excellence in Education program, including a program description and list of projects funded in 1992-1993.
      - Proposal Review Process, 1994 March 10-September 30 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 1637
        Documents for the proposal review process for the Excellence in Education program, 1994.
      - Summaries of Grant Projects, 1994 November 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 1558
        Summaries of Grant Projects for the Excellence in Education program, November 1994.
      - AAHE School College Collaboration Conference, 1995 October 26-28 (Box 2, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 1624
        Meeting materials for the American Association for Higher Education's (AAHE) School College Collaboration Conference held in Washington, D.C., October 26-28, 1995.
      - Overview of Grant Program, 1995 March 14-19 (Box 2, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 1636
        Overview of the Excellence in Education grant program, 1995.
      - Summaries of Grant Projects, 1995 October 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
        Knight File Number - 767
        Summaries of grant projects for the Excellence in Education Initiative. Created for the American Association for Higher Education and the Education Trust's Sixth National Conference on School/College Collaboration.
      - Transition Grants, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 8)
        Knight File Number - 1635
        Criteria for rating proposals for transition grants in the Excellence in Education program, and rating sheets, 1995.
      - AAHE School College Collaboration Conference, 1996 November 24 (Box 2, Folder 9)
        Knight File Number - 1627
        Meeting materials for the American Association for Higher Education's (AAHE) School College Collaboration Conference held in Washington, D.C. November 20-24, 1996.
      - AAHE School College Collaboration Conference, 1997 November 20-22 (Box 2, Folder 10)
        Knight File Number - 1628
        Meeting materials for the American Association for Higher Education's (AAHE) School College Collaboration Conference held in Washington, D.C. November 20-22, 1997.
      - Summaries of Grant Projects, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 11)
        Knight File Number - 1156
        Summaries of grant projects in the Excellence in Education Program, 1997. Includes projects from: University of Akron, California State University at Dominguez Hills, University of Colorado at Boulder, Columbia College, Columbus State University, Commonwealth Partnership, Cumberland College, Florida A&M University, Florida International University, Florida State University, Gallaudet University, Haverford College, Heritage College, Indiana University Northwest, Johns Hopkins University, Juniata College, Mercer University, Mount Holyoke and Hampshire Colleges, University of North Carolina at Charlotte and Central Piedmont Community College, University of North Dakota, Northern State University, University of Pennsylvania, College of St. Scholastica, University of St. Thomas, University of Southern Mississippi, Stetson University.
      - AAHE School College Collaboration Conference, 1998 November 12-14 (Box 2, Folder 12)
        Knight File Number - 1630
        Meeting materials for the American Association for Higher Education's (AAHE) School College Collaboration Conference held in Washington, D.C. November 12-14, 1998.
      - Summaries of Grant Projects, 1998 November (Box 2, Folder 13)
        Knight File Number - 4090
        Through the Excellence in Education Program, KF sought to help strengthen all levels of education by encouraging colleges and schools to rethink their interrelationships and to view education reform as a broader challenge. This report provides brief summaries by grantee institutions on success/failures of their grants.
      - AAHE School College Collaboration Conference, 1999 November 11-13 (Box 2, Folder 14)
        Knight File Number - 1629
        Meeting materials for the American Association for Higher Education's (AAHE) School College Collaboration Conference held in Washington, D.C. November 11-13, 1999.
    - Initiatives - Excellence in Undergraduate Education, 1986-1998; 6.5
      The Excellence in Undergraduate Education initiative provided nearly $10 million in competitive grants to forty strong, private, liberal arts colleges in the sixteen states where Knight Foundation communities are located.
      A dissemination conference was held in 1993, and the Archives holds the records of that conference. Transcripts from the television show "Firing Line," which was sponsored by Knight Foundation during the conference, are included, as well as meeting agenda and materials. A booklet produced by Knight Foundation in 1993 entitled "Summaries of Grant Projects and Program Description" is contained in this subseries, as well as a 1993 update on the program, which was sent to the Distribution Committee. There is also another booklet entitled "Summaries of Grant Projects." It was produced in 1995 for the American Association for Higher Education and the Education Trust.
      - Development of Education Initiative, 1986 August 19-December 12 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 1642
        Correspondence outlining the development of the education initiative, 1986.
      - Policy to Guide Educational Grants, 1987 December 4-1988 January 21 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 1641
        Correspondence relating to a policy to guide educational grants.
      - Planning for the Education Program, 1988 February 16-October 25 (Box 3, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 1640
        Correspondence relating to the planning of the Education program, 1988.
      - Program Guidelines, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 1505
        Excellence in Undergraduate Education Program Guidelines. This was the Education Program's first initiative.
      - First Round of Grants, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 1644
        List of invitees to the first round of grants in the Excellence in Undergraduate Education program, 1989.
      - Second Round of Grants, 1989 July 13-November 22 (Box 3, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 1638
        Correspondence relating to the second round of grants for the Excellence in Undergraduate Education program, 1989.
      - Grant Program--planning, nominees, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
        Knight File Number - 1639
        Correspondence relating to the planning of grants and the nominees for the Excellence in Undergraduate Education program, 1989.
      - Proposal Review Process, 1990 April 4-December 11 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
        Knight File Number - 1643
        Documents from the proposal review process for the Excellence in Undergraduate Education grants, 1990. 2 folders.
      - Program Guidelines, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
        Knight File Number - 1646
        Published Program Guidelines for the Excellence in Undergraduate Education program, 1991.
      - Proposal Review Process, 1991 March 8-April 11 (Box 3, Folder 11)
        Knight File Number - 1645
        Documents from the proposal review process for the Excellence in Undergraduate Education grants, 1991.
      - Dissemination Conference for Liberal Arts Colleges, 1993 June 10-12 (Box 3, Folder 12)
        Knight File Number - 1649
        Materials for the Dissemination Conference for Liberal Arts Colleges held in Columbia, MD on June 10-12, 1993.
      - Excellence in Undergraduate Education Conference, 1993 June 10-12 (Box 3, Folder 13)
        Knight File Number - 731
        Materials distributed for Excellence in Undergraduate Education Conference (A Dissemination Conference for Liberal Arts Colleges) at Columbia, MD, June 19-12, 1993. Materials include meeting agenda, kit for participants and media (including description of the Excellence in Undergraduate Education program).
      - Excellence in Undergraduate Education Conference, "Firing Line" Transcripts, 1993 June 10-12 (Box 3, Folder 14)
        Knight File Number - 732
        Transcripts of the television show "Firing Line," hosted by William F. Buckley, which was sponsored by the Knight Foundation during the Excellence in Undergraduate Conference. The topics of the show were: "What is Liberal Education," "The Class of '93 With Honors," "Who Should be Liberally Educated," and "Why Does College Cost So Much?"
      - Grant Dissemination Publication Planning, 1993 August 10-September 30 (Box 3, Folder 15)
        Knight File Number - 1647
        Planning materials for the grant dissemination publication for the Excellence in Undergraduate Education program, 1993.
      - Excellence in Undergraduate Education: Summaries of Grant Projects, 1993 June-December (Box 3, Folder 16)
        Knight File Number - 733
        Spiral bound bookets assembled by Knight Foundation in June and December 1993, (titled Excellence In Educaton) which include a description of the Excellence in Undergraduate Education program and summaries of its grant projects by college. Also included are a statement of purpose of the Knight Foundation, and the list of members of the Education Advisory Committee.
      - Summaries of the impact of the grant program, 1993 July 2-August 10 (Box 3, Folder 17)
        Knight File Number - 1648
        Summaries from college officials of the impact of the Excellence in Undergraduate Education grant program, 1993.
    - Initiatives - Presidential Leadership Program, 1989-2000; 6.6
      The Presidential Leadership Grant Program, 1989-1993, provided ten discretionary grants of $100,000 each to small, tuition-dependent colleges serving special populations (such as women and minorities). The use of the funds was left to the discretion of the president of each college.
      These files date from 1989 to 1993. They contain background and planning materials, rankings of the proposed recipients and recommendations, an overview of this phase of the program, including use of the grants by the recipients, and materials from a meeting of the college presidents who received the grants.
      - Presidential Leadership Program, Phase I, 1989 October 27-1993 June 24 (Box 1, Folder 6-12)
        Knight File Number - 287
        Records of Education program to reward outstanding leadership of selected college presidents with unrestricted grants. Phase I of the program took place in 1990/91. Records include correspondence re: background and planning of the program, 1990 and 1991 rankings and recommendations for grant awardees (including writeups of each grant), and an overview of the program (use of grants by recipients) and its progress, 1990-1993.
      - Presidential Leadership Grant Program, Phase II, 1996 August 15-2000 April 18 (Box 4, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 4078
        Records of Education program to reward outstanding leadership of selected college presidents with unrestricted grants. Phase II of the program took place from 1996 to 1999. Records include correspondence re: background and planning of the program, rankings and recommendations for grant awardees (including writeups of each grant), and meeting schedules and participant lists.
      - Evaluation for Knight Foundation by Mary Maples Dunn, 1999 April (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
        Knight File Number - 4079
        Evaluation took into account how the grants were used, the college and community response to the grants, and their effectiveness. The evaluation was based largely on conversations that Dunn had with the college presidents.
    - Program Director's Files, 1987-2000; 6.7
      This subseries contains files related to the Knight Foundation's early interest and activities in literacy. It includes the files of Sarah Wright from 1987 to 1990, when she headed the Foundation's Education efforts in Akron. Among the literacy files are responses to a 1987 letter from Rolfe Neill to publishers in Knight-Ridder cities (now considered community advisers) asking them to identify opportunities for literacy funding in their communities. This file, titled "Knight-Ridder Newspaper Involvement Questionnaire," is significant to the Foundation's efforts in the field of literacy because it is cited by president Creed Black as "one of the more effective early efforts by Knight Foundation to target funding and utilize the network of community advisers to be proactive in identifying good funding opportunities."
      Other files included are a summary of Knight Foundation literacy projects 1985-1986, correspondence regarding the formation and activities of the Literacy Task Force for the North American Newspaper Industry (Creed Black was a member of this task force when it operated in 1988-1989), a brochure on the Kenan Family Trust Literacy Project (related to the Foundation's eventual major funding of the National Center for Family Literacy), and other correspondence on Knight Foundation literacy efforts.
      There is one file that contains a memo by Education Program Director A. Richardson Love, titled "Education Program Evaluation Activity." It gives an overview and history of Knight Foundation's activities and initiatives in the Education Program from 1989 to 1997.
      - Literacy: Knight-Ridder Newspaper Involvement Questionnaire, 1987 February 11-April 27 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 735
        NULL
      - Literacy Programs: Summary of Knight Foundation literacy projects in 1985-86, 1987 February 9 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 1024
        This folder contains a letter by C.C. Gibson to the American Newspaper Publishers Association Foundation, discussing three literacy projects funded by the Knight Foundation: Friends of the Detroit Public Library, the City of Philadelphia, and the Business Council for Effective Literacy.
      - Literacy Programs: correspondence re: newspaper literary task force, 1988 June 3-1988 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 1025
        Correspondence between Creed Black, Sarah Wright, Jay Ambrose and Larry Jinks regarding the formation of a national newspaper literacy task force.
      - Literacy Programs: Brochure on the Kenan Family Trust Literacy Project, 1989 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 1026
        Knight Foundation's interest in literacy projects is shown in this folder. It contains a brochure from the Kenan Family Trust Literacy Project, which documents the background of the National Center for Family Literacy and the Kenan Trust/Bill Friday connection to KF's later major funding for the center.
      - Literacy Programs: Correspondence and Proposal for National Literacy Corps., 1989 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 1027
        Correspondence from Henry King Stanford regarding literacy training, and a proposal from the National Literacy Corps for Knight Foundation support of its literacy program.
      - Literacy Programs: Task Force for the North American Newspaper Industry, 1989 February 20-July 31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 1035
        Correspondence between Jay Ambrose of the Rocky Mountain News and Sarah Wright regarding Knight Foundation's participation in the Newspaper Literacy Task Force. Knight Foundation decided not to participate in this task force.
      - Literacy Programs: Correspondence re: planning for a Knight Foundation literacy program, 1989 July 26-1990 December 11 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Knight File Number - 1036
        Correspondence between Sarah Wright and the director of Literacy South, in which Sarah mentions Knight Foundation's stage in planning for its literacy program.
      - Literacy Programs: working papers on a literacy "white paper" for a Knight Foundation literacy program, 1990 June 15-18 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Knight File Number - 1037
        Knight Foundation Literacy project: working papers on a literacy "white paper" commissioned by KF to examine potential grantmaking in the field of literacy. Includes a draft of the white paper by Carolyn Chandler (edited by James Harvey).
      - Different Ways of Knowing: The Galef Institute and Knight Foundation, 1993 October-1999 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
        Knight File Number - 4162